Preliminary Guide to the International Counterculture Archive, 1990-2003 GRC0003
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Counterculture Archive
1990-2003
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Yoffe, Mark
GRC0003
12 Linear Feet
This collection contains printed and handwritten materials: magazines, almanacs, "fanzines", newsletters, manuscripts, books, posters, fliers, leaflets and other forms of printed ephemera; audio: self-produced, small label etc. recordings of music, poetry, verbal art, speeches, lectures, performances; video recordings: self-produced, small label, or homemade videos pertaining to the subject; film: self-produced, small label, or homemade films pertaining to the subject; photographs documenting countercultural activities; and ephemera and works of plastic arts.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Curator Mark Yoffe actively collects the materials that make up this Archive.
Historical Note
The International Counterculture Archive has the goal of collecting multimedia materials produced by, or dealing with, countercultural groups and movements of different countries. The Archive serves as a depositary for such a collection and provides assistance, expertise, necessary networking to scholars from different fields involved in the study of countercultural movements. The Archive is an interdisciplinary body. In addition to acquisition and processing of the materials, the Archive provides bibliographic description of the collection, reference support and serves as a link for scholars and collectors working in the field. Counterculture groups and movements are defined as existing within any modern society and in any country which find themselves in opposition to governing and accepted mainstream ideology, values and the approved and sanctioned forms of self expression. Counterculture is a culture of opposition and minorities. It can be highly political and/or purely artistic, but it inevitably finds itself in opposition to the mainstream political thinking, aesthetical perceptions, styles, and forms and ways of self expression.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains printed and handwritten materials: magazines, almanacs, "fanzines", newsletters, manuscripts, books, posters, fliers, leaflets and other forms of printed ephemera; audio: self-produced, small label etc. recordings of music, poetry, verbal art, speeches, lectures, performances; video recordings: self-produced, small label, or homemade videos pertaining to the subject; film: self-produced, small label, or homemade films pertaining to the subject; photographs documenting countercultural activities; and ephemera and works of plastic arts.
These materials address subjects such as political movements including right and left fringe, nationalism, labor, terrorism, lobbying bodies; Bohemian movements: literary and artistic groups and movements; music movements and performance art: jazz, folk, rock'n'roll, avant garde; youth movements: mods, hippies, punk, post/punk/new wave, hippie revivalism, cyber-punk and others; drug subculture; feminism; gay subculture; green and "back to nature" movements; neo pagan movements; and Indigenous group movements.
Though the Archive's collection policy is truly global in scope currently collecting activity centers on two distinct areas: Russia, CIS (commonwealth of independent states) countries, Eastern Europe and the Balkans; and the Washington, D.C. metropolitan area.
Please note: this collection has unprocessed portions. Please see staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Only a small portion of this collectin is processed. When processing is complete, this small portion will most likely be designated as a series titled Counterculture zines.
Counterculture -- Russia (Federation); Counterculture -- Ukraine; Counterculture -- Latvia; Counterculture -- Poland -- Periodicals; Counterculture -- Washington (D.C.); Photographs
- OKOROK, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General note
  Publishing information: No. 1 (16), 1991; No. 10, 1993-1994 (Sentiabr' 1993 - Ianvar' 1994) Mogilev, Belarus
- KONTR KUL'T UR'a (Kontrkul'tura), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Publishing information: No. 2, 1990 MOSKVA, Russia
- APRAKSIN BLIUZ (APRAKSIN BLUES): GREATEST HITS IN INTRANSLATION, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Publishing information: No. 1, 2002; Seaside, CA, USA; Founded in St. Petersburg, Russia, Sept. 1995
- APRAKSIN BLIUZ, SIGNAL' NYI VYPUSK, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Publishing information: No. 11, 2003; SEASIDE, CA, USA (In Russian)
- APRAKSIN BLIUZ, SIGNAL EDITION English edition, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Publishing information: No. 10/18, 2002; Monterey, CA, USA. (In English)
- BRUTTO, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Publishing information: No. 7, SUMMER 1991; No. 1/11, JANUARY 1992; No. 2/12, FEB-MAR 1992; No. 5/15, SUMMER 1992; STERLIKAMSK, RUSSIA
- GOTHIC: UNDERGROUND METAL ZINE, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Publishing information: No. 3, [1993?] MOSKVA, RUSSIA
- KHIPPILEND, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Publishing information: No. 1, 1993; No. 2, 1993 (2 copies); No. 5, 1995; SANKT PETERSBURG, RUSSIA
- ZABRISKI RIDER, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Publishing information: No. 6-7, OSEN' 1997 - ZIMA 1998 (Fall 97-Winter 98); No. 4, LETO-OSEN' 1996 (Summer-Fall 1996); MOSCOW, RUSSIA
- URLAIT, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Publishing information: No. 7, 1989; AL'MANAKH "URLAIT" 91, 1991 (LAST URLAIT PUBLISHED); MOSCOW, RUSSIA
- PROK, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Publishing information: No. 2, July 1990; (ZHURNAL POK-STUDII "ANDERGRAUND"), (MAGAZINE OF BAKU, AZERBAJDZHAN Rock Studio "Underground"); PUBLISHED SINCE JUNE 1990; BAKU, AZERBAJDZHAN
- Zabriski Point, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Publishing information: 1992, MOSCOW, Russia
- NADRYVY, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Publishing information: No. 1, 1990; KIEV, UKRAINE
- Tapki, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Publishing information: No. 2, Feb. 1991; (VESTNIK ROK-ASSOTSIATSII RIM); RIAZAN', RUSSIA
- URLAIT, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Publishing information: No. 9, 1985; No. 10, JAN-FEB 1986; MOSCOW, RUSSIA
- RUK OKO, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Publishing information: No. 2, IIUN' (June) 1990; No. 3, DEKABR' (December) 1990; Baku, Azerbajdzhan
- UNDERGROUND, ANDERGRAUND, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Publishing information: No. 7, DEC. 1992; ISHIM, TIUMEN' OBL., RUSSIA (SIBERIA)
- SDVIG, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Publishing information: [1990?]; MOSKVA, RUSSIA
- KAS EKSPRESS, 03/15/1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Publishing information: No. 3, 3-15-1995 MOSKVA, RUSSIA
- VOLIA: MEZHUDUNARODNAIA ANARKHICHESKAIA GAZETA, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Publishing information: No. 7, OCT.-NOV. 1994; No. 8, JAN-FEB. 1995; MOSKVA, RUSSIA
- CHERNAIA ZVEZDA, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Publishing information: No. 1 (12) 1995; MOSKVA, RUSSIA
- KHERR, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Publishing information: No. 2, Dec. 1990-March 1991; No. 3, 1991-WINTER 1992; No. 3, 1991 (INCLUDES 2 POSTERS); TITLE FOR No. 3 (1991 - WINTER 1992) IS: KHER BEZ MASLA, TWO OTHER VOLS. HAVE TITLE: KHER S MASLOM; OREKHOVO-ZUEVO, RUSSIA
- VUGLUSKR, 11/1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Publishing information: No. 1, NOV. 1993; MOSCOW, RUSSIA
- POP-MAGAZIN, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Publishing information: No. 2-3 (5-6), 1991; No. 7, 1992; MOSCOW, RUSSIA
- P. STONE, 08/1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Publishing information: No. 5, AUGUST 1991; [MOSCOW?] RUSSIA
- ERES', 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Publishing information: No. 8, 1991-1992; No. 9, 1992?; VENTSPILS, RIGA, LATVIA
- ROKADA, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Publishing information: No. 2, 1991; MOSCOW, RUSSIA
- AOR (ARCHIVE OF OMSK ROCK) (ARKHIV OMSKOGO ROKA), 04/1990-03/1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Publishing information: No. 2, APR.-JUNE 90; No. 4, OCT.-DEC. 90; No. 5, JAN.-MARCH 91; OMSK, RUSSIA
- POSPEDNIAIA OKHOTA, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Publishing information: No. 4-5, 1993; Kolomna, RUSSIA
- URA BUM BUM!, NO. 9, 1992? ROSTOV-NA-DOXU, RUSSIA (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Publishing information: No. 9, 1992(?); Rostov-na-Donu, Russia
- ZHURIVAL AKUREKU!, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Publishing information: [199?] [MOSCOW?] RUSSIA; (Published by Indi Klub AKU) Editor, Opga Aref'eva (well known Russian singer-songwriter)
- MITSAR, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Publishing information: No. 1, 1992; No. 2, 1992; Bol'shoi Kamen', Primorskii Krai, (Siberia), Russia
- RUSSKII ROK, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Publishing information: No. 1, 1993; MOSKVA, RUSSIA
- KHUDOZHESTVENNAIA VOLIA, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Publishing information: No. 6, 1993 (?); No. 7, 1993; SANKT-PETERBURG, RUSSIA
- KHOMER, 06/1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Publishing information: NO. 1, 06. 1994; ISRAEL?
- POL'SKII BATON, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Publishing information: No. 17, 1995; SPETSIAL'NOE PRILOZHENIE K ZHURNALU "POL'SKII BATON", (ZHURNAL 3; No. 1)
- O. R. Z. (OSTROE RESPIRATORNOE ZABOLEVANIE), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Publishing information: No. 1 (6), 1992; OMSK, RUSSIA (SIBERIA)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0001)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0002)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0003)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0004)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0005)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0006)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0007)
- Counterculture archives, undated (Box UP0008)